<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the 3 of Nouember 1594. intreating of the second comming of Christ, and the disclosing of Antichrist. : With a confutation of diuerse coniectures concerning the end of the world, conteyned in a booke intituled, The second comming of Christ. / Preached by Iohn Dove.</title>
            <author>Dove, John,</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7086.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52633179</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52633179</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01207)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2114:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the 3 of Nouember 1594. intreating of the second comming of Christ, and the disclosing of Antichrist. : With a confutation of diuerse coniectures concerning the end of the world, conteyned in a booke intituled, The second comming of Christ. / Preached by Iohn Dove.</title>
                  <author>Dove, John,</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Newly perused, corrected, and the second time imprinted.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by V.S. for VVilliam Iaggard, and are to be sold at his shop in Fleetstreet in Saint Dunstans Churchyard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1594?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Headpieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with loss of print from t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John, 1st, II, 18 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Second Advent --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173988:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON, Preached at Pauls Croſſe, <hi>the 3. of Nouember</hi> 1594. intreating of the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſing of Antichriſt. <hi>With a confutation of diuerſe</hi> coniectures concerning the end of the world, conteyned in a Booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, The ſecond comming of Chriſt. Newly peruſed, corrected, and the ſecond time imprinted. Preached by Iohn Doue.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Reu 1.</bibl> Behold, he commeth in the Clouds, and euerie eye ſhall ſee him.</q>
            <p>Imprinted by V. S. for VVilliam Iaggard, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Fleetſtreet in Saint Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans Churchyard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173988:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173988:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt vertuous and Noble Gentleman, Maiſter Frances Gorges.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoeuer loueth not the Lord Ieſus, let him be Anathema maran atha, had in execration euen to the death. But I know that you haue loued him from your cradle, forſomuch as you haue bin no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed vp in the words of faith, and wholſome doctrine, which you haue continually imbraced. Wherefore, in him, whom you haue thus loued, (ſo long as you ceaſe not to loue him) I alſo loue you as my ſoule, and tender your ſaluation as mine owne. The God, euen the father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, whom you ſerue, and who is bleſſed for euermore, knoweth that I lie not. And, howbeit, the preaching of the croſſe is fooliſhneſſe to them that periſh: yet ſeeing it hath pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſſe of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to ſaue them that beleeue, you muſt ſuffer a little this my fooliſhneſſe, which am gealous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you with a godly gealoſy. Therfore! charge you before God, and the L. Ieſus Chriſt which ſhall iudge the quicke and the dead at his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and in his kingdome, that you decline not
<pb facs="tcp:173988:3"/> to the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, nor to the left, neither to ſchiſm nor poperie, but hate them both, as hitherto you haue done, with a perfect hatred. And though you be yong in yeares, yet be not a child in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, carried about with euery wind of doctrine by the deceit of men, and with crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whereby they lay in wait to deceiue: but fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the truth in loue, and in al things grow vp into him which is the head, that is Chriſt. And ſo doing, aſſure your ſelfe, that hee which hath begun this good worke in you, will performe it, vntill the day of Ieſus Chriſt. God the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which according to his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant mercie hath begotten you againe vnto a liuely hope, by the reſurrection of his ſonne from the dead to an inheritance immortall and vndefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerued in heauen for you, bleſſe you and guide you with his holy ſpirit, that you may increaſe in wiſdom in ſtature, in fauor with God and man, and ſo multiply his graces vpon you, that you may goe forward from vertue to vertue, from grace to grace, and grant that at the length we may meet together vnto a perfect man, and to the meaſure of the age of the fulneſſe of Christ.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, Iohn Doue.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:173988:3"/>
            <head>A Sermon of the ſecond comming of Chriſt, and the diſcloſing of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. Iohn, 2, verſe 18.</bibl> Little children, it is the laſt houre, and as ye haue heard that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſhal come, euen nowe are there many Antichriſtes: whereby we know that it is the laſt houre.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Briefe admonition, concerning the final conſummation and end of the world. In which admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I obſerue theſe two things: firſt a bare and ſimple affirmation, that it is not only in the ſtaggering &amp; declining age, but, which exceedeth dotage, at the verie vpſhot, and like a ſicke man which lyeth at deaths doore, ready to breath out the laſt gaſpe, in theſe words: <hi>Litle children, it is the laſt houre.</hi> Secondly, an argument for proofe and confirmation therof, which is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Antichriſt; in theſe words: <hi>Ye haue heard that Antichriſt ſhall come, euen now are there many Antichriſts, whereby we know that it is the laſt houre,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Litle children it is the laſt houre</hi> Beſides the common and vſuall ſignification, an houre is
<pb facs="tcp:173988:4"/> diuerſly vnderſtood in the holy ſcriptures, ſometimes for the fear and horror of death, our Sauiour being in his agonie prayeth to his father in this maner: <hi>My ſoule is troubled:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 12.</note> 
               <hi>father ſaue me from this houre,</hi> and that porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſorrow which in Saint Mathew is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a cup, is alſo called an houre, <hi>Father if it</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mar. 14.</note> 
               <hi>be poſsible let this houre paſſe away from me:</hi> Sometimes for the laſt period of mans life: <note place="margin">Iohn 13. Rom. 13.</note> 
               <hi>He knew that his hour was come that he ſhould depart out of this worlde vnto his father:</hi> Thirdly for any oportunitie and fitneſſe of time: <hi>now the houre is come that we ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake out of ſleepe for our redemption draweth nearer then when we firſt beleeued.</hi> Fourthly, for any ſmall moment, or inſtant, farre ſhorter than an houre, as, when he ſent his Diſciples as ſheepe among wolues, hee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them with pacience, ſaying: <hi>When they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall deliuer you vp, take no thought, howe, or what ye ſhall anſwere,</hi> for, <hi>vobis dabitur in il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la hora, It ſhall be giuen you in that houre.</hi> But, in this place it is taken more largely, for houres, dayes and yeares, and all diſtance of time, betweene the firſt comming of Chriſt in humilitie, and his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in maieſtie. For ſince this epiſtle was written, 1500, yeares are alreadie expired,
<pb facs="tcp:173988:4"/> and yet the hour not ended, which time ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to man a date very long, <hi>Which dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob. 4.</note> 
               <hi>in a houſe of clay, whoſe foundation is in the duſt, who ſhall be deſtroyed before the moth, whoſe fleſh is clothed with wormes, and whoſe memorie may he compared to aſhes:</hi> who neuer liueth the third part of the yeares of the Hart, which <hi>brayeth after the water</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41. Mat. 24. Pſal. 39.</note> 
               <hi>brooke,</hi> or the rauen which preyeth vpon the <hi>dead carkas,</hi> nay rather, <hi>Whoſe life is but a ſpan long, and as nothing before God.</hi> To man I ſay, it ſeemeth long, becauſe his life is very ſhort, but to God which is euerlaſting, a ſcantling verie briefe, and therefore fitly called an houre. For, what is one droppe of water to the Ocean ſea? one graine of Wheate to all the corne threſhed on the barne floare after harueſt? one grape to all the cluſters preſſed in the winefatte at the time of vintage? one acre of ground in the viewe of the mappe of all the world? the life of the abortiue and vntimely fruit of a woman, to the age of Methuſalem, the thoughts of a foole to the wiſdome of Salomon, which had a large heart as the ſandes of the ſea, the knowledge of newe born babes to the experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Noah, which ſaw two worldes, the old and the new: the
<pb facs="tcp:173988:5"/> center of the earth, to the Circumference of heauen a right line to a circle: one houre to many thouſand yeares: the ſame is this laſt period of the world, beeing compared with eternitie, which neuer began, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall end. As alſo for two other reaſons, that conſidering the time is ſo ſhort, it may be an incitement to ſtirre vp the godly, and a conſolation to comfort the afflicted: to make the godly watchfull; for ſo writeth Peter: <hi>the ende of all things is at hand, be ye</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4</note> 
               <hi>therefore ſober and watchfull in prayer,</hi> to arm the afflicted with patience, ſeeing they haue but a litle tribulation to endure, ſo ſaith our Sauiour: <hi>When you ſee theſe things begin</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luc. 21.</note> 
               <hi>to come to paſſe, then looke vp, and lift vp your heads, for your redemption draweth neer.</hi> And rebuking the drowſineſſe of Peter, Iames, and Iohn, he draweth argument of repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion from the breuitie of the time, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>could ye not haue watched with mee one</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mar. 14.</note> 
               <hi>houre?</hi> Seeing it is but an houre, we muſt not be heauie, as the Apoſtles which ſlept, nor looſe as Sathan, which the neerer he is to his iudgement, the more he rageth: nor enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as the euill tenant, which when his leaſe is almoſt expired, maketh waſt and hauock: but patient like trauellers, which are leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:173988:5"/> wearie being almoſt at their iourneys end: and vigilant as the faithfull ſeruant, which when he is neere his freedom, is more du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull in his ſeruice, becauſe he hath but a ſhort time to ſerue.</p>
            <p>But for my better proceeding, and your edifying, in my two houres diſcourſe of this one and laſt houre, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the firſt part, theſe four points in particular by Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious aſsiſtance, and your chriſtian patience are to be diſcuſſed. Firſt, of the weakneſſe of their arguments which hold this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; that the worlde ſhall neuer haue an end. Secondly, their raſhneſſe is to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, which make a ſhew of diuinitie, but in deed ſet abroch their owne conceits, and priuate phantaſies, and ſo vnaduiſedly take vpon them to demonſtrate when the world muſt haue an end. Thirdly, how far we may bee bold to determin, hauing firſt with iudgement and ſobrietie looked into the ſtate of this queſtion. Fourthly, after it ſhall be made euident, that the kingdom of God is not now <hi>è longinquo,</hi> but <hi>è propinquo</hi> not a far off, but euen at our doores, how we ought to behaue our ſelues in the meane time, expecting the moſt bleſſed comming of our Sauiour Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173988:6"/>
            <p>Concerning the firſt point, two ſortes of men denie that the world ſhal haue an end, Philoſophers and Atheiſts: The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers <note place="margin">Phyſ. l. 8.</note> draw their proofes from naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Atheiſts from Diuinitie, both are controlled by this place. The Philoſophers argue out of Ariſtotle, that the worlde ſhall haue no ende, becauſe it had no beginning; that it had no beginning, becauſe it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in motion; that it was alwayes in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe God in whom all other things haue their being and mouing, euer moued it, for nothing els could be moued by him if the world were not, and if he did not alwais moue as nowe hee doth, he is not conſtant, and permanent in one eſtate, but ſubiect to chaunge, which is an abſurditie, and may not be graunted. But, becauſe, ſuch curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie doth not edifie, and I am not to play the Philoſopher in this place, and faith is not agreeable to naturall reaſon, I anſwere Ariſtotle the mirrour of humaine witte, not by witte or humaine reaſon, for that I can not, but againſt him I oppoſe the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Saint Paule: <hi>Where is the diſputer?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> 
               <hi>hath not God made the wiſdome of this worlde fooliſhneſſe? ſeeing the world by wiſdome knew not God in the wiſdome of God, it pleaſed God</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:173988:6"/> 
               <hi>through the fooliſhneſſe of preaching to ſaue them that beleeue.</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>that which is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3.</note> 
               <hi>fleſh is fleſhly.</hi> Ariſtotle, though the wiſeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles, was a ſenſuall man, and therefore vnderſtood not the things which were of God.</p>
            <p>I come to the Atheiſts; which (as Beza <note place="margin">In anotat. in Pet. 2. Pet. 8.</note> writeth) are in the courts of Princes. Of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith Peter. <hi>This firſt vnderſtand, that there ſhall come in the latter dayes mockers, which ſhall willbe after their owne luſtes, and ſay: where is the promiſe of his comming? for ſince the fathers ſlept, ad things haue continued alike from the firſt creation.</hi> In the which wordes, they draw a weake argument from the long continuance of the worlde, to prooue the perpetuitie of the ſame, and conclude this enthymem: <hi>The worlde hath euer continued alike from the firſt Creation, therfore it ſhall alwaies ſo continue.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle maketh anſwere to the antecedent two maner of wayes. Firſt, hee denieth it to be true by a notable inſtance, for once (ſaith he) the world was deſtroied by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of water, therefore all things haue not continued alike from the firſt creation. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> beſides that the long continuance of the worlde, if it were graunted, were no
<pb facs="tcp:173988:7"/> argument to proue the perpetuitie of the ſame: he anſwereth by a diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that this long continuance were long in reſpect of men only, &amp; not of God, ſo that theſe 5500 yeares, which are commonly reckoned from the firſt creation vntill this age, are but as fiue daies and an halfe in the ſight of God, a verie ſhort time, which ſaint Peter proueth by the authoritie of the Prophet, <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.</note> who affirmeth that a thouſand yeares are with God as ſhort as one day, euen as one day with God, is as long as a thouſand years with men.</p>
            <p>Hauing anſwered the obiection of the Atheiſts, the Apoſtle diſputeth againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by an argument <hi>à ſimili</hi> in this maner. <hi>Euen as the old world</hi> (meaning the earth) <hi>which was of the water, and by the water, had her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and continuance by the word of God, and by the ſame word of God, and the ſame waters it periſhed: ſo the new world</hi> (meaning both hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth) <hi>are by the ſame word kept in ſtore and reſerued to fire.</hi> Aſmuch as if he had ſaid: before the floud, the world continued long, yet at length it was deſtroyed by the ſame thing of which it conſiſted, which was the element of water, ſo after the floud it hath continued longer, yet it is the ſecond
<pb facs="tcp:173988:7"/> time to be deſtroyed of the other element of which it conſiſteth, which is fire. When the floud had ceaſed, the Lord gaue the rainbow for a token of his couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t between <note place="margin">Gen. 9.</note> him and vs, but in the rainbow are eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee obſerued two things, the figure there of, and the colours whereby it is made viſible vnto our eies: the figure is like a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micircle cut off in the middle by our Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, ſo that to our ſight it ſeemeth to reach from the higheſt arch of heauen, to the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt foundation of the earth, to ſignifie, that for as much as man which dwelleth in the loweſt earth, offended him which fitteth in <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> the higheſt heauen, Gods mercie pierced the clouds, and deſcended from the higheſt heauen to the loweſt foundation of the earth vnto the ſonnes of men. But the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours where with it is beautified, are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally two; the one is a Sea-colour, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth Water, where with it was drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the other fierie, betokening the other Element, wherunto the world vntil the day of iudgement is reſerued.</p>
            <p>The Philoſophers and Atheiſts beeing gainſaid, which affirme that the world ſhall neuer haue an ende: it followeth that wee touch the ſecond kinde of men, which are
<pb facs="tcp:173988:8"/> Chriſtians, but of two ſorts, Proteſtants and Papiſts, which both expect the acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this laſt houre, but erre in this, that they go another way too far, and ſeeming to know that which they know not, enter into the ſecrets of God: the Proteſtants di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, and the Papiſts by a neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, do define and determine when the world ſhall haue an end. And therefore as the Apoſtle ſaith: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> when they profeſſed themſelues wiſe, they became fooliſh. Some Proteſtants haue publiſhed a booke greatly eſteemed of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the common people, in which is maintayned this argument: That the frame of Heauen muſt needes be diſſolued <note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d comming of Chriſt.</note> within a certainty of daies: and the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall reaſons whereby they vndertake the proofe of their phantaſies, are theſe fiue which follow.</p>
            <p>The firſt is a blind propheſie which they father vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Elias, not read of in the ſcripturs but in the Rabbies &amp; Talmud of the Iewes, that the worlde could laſt but ſix thouſand years after the firſt creation, two thouſand vnder nature, two thouſand vnder the law, and two thouſand vnder grace. The time of nature they define to be from the firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:173988:8"/> to Abraham, to whom the law of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was giuen: the time of the law fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Abraham to the preaching of Iohn the Baptiſt, which began in the 30. yeare of the incarnation of Chriſt: the time of grace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preaching of Iohn to the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And (ſay they) as Elias liued after the firſt 3000. yeares were expired, and then was taken vp aliue in his fierie chariot, ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the other 3000. yeares ſhall be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, thoſe that ſhalbe found at that time quicke on the earth, muſt bee taken vp in the cloudes to meete our Sauiour comming to iudgement. For anſwere whereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that they erre in their computation of yeares, which is manifeſt to them which are conuerſant in the Hiſtories of the bible, we vtterly denie, and renounce the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Rabbies and Iewiſh Talmud as ſuperſtitious and falſe, not giuing credite to any thing which is written of Elias in them, more than may be proued out of the moſt holy ſcriptures, and ſo conſequently denying that Elias euer writ anie ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, wee diſplaye the weakeneſſe of that argument, in this manner. It is a rule Logicke, that a ſimilitude muſt not holde in all things, but onely in that
<pb facs="tcp:173988:9"/> whereto it is applied. Wherefore foraſmuch as Paul writeth: <hi>That we ſhall not all ſleepe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> becauſe, as it is in the article of our <hi>Creede,</hi> Chriſt ſhall come to iudge both the quicke and the dead, true it is that Elias which was taken vp quicke, was a liuely tipe of them which ſhall be found quicke at the day of iudgement: for, as he was taken vp aliue, ſo they muſt bee taken vp aliue without taſting of death, onely their corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bodies beeing chaunged: but it is no good conſequent, either in Logicke or Diuinitie, that bicauſe Elias was a type of them in this one thing, therefore as Elias was taken vp after the firſt 3000. yeares, therefore they muſt alſo be taken vp, when the other 3000. yeares be ended. The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiencie of this argument I will ſhewe you by the like. Henoch was a type of them which ſhall bee found quicke at the day of Iudgement, as well as Elias, But He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch was taken vp aliue, and tranſlated to a better life, in the 987. yeare of the worlde: if therefore the former argument drawne from Elias bee good, this alſo muſt follow, that the day of iudgement ſhould haue bin nine hundred eightie ſeuen yeares after the tranſlation of Henoch, ſo that the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:173988:9"/> ſhould not haue endured in all, two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares after the firſt creation. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, they affirme, that ſome part of the laſt thouſand yeares muſt be defalcated and cut off, for the elects ſake, which is a meere contradiction to that which went before, for then can not the propheſie which they father vpon Elias be true, that the worlde ſhould continue 6000. yeares. And this defalcation of yeares they proue by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of the Angell <hi>vriel,</hi> which beeing asked whether the time to come were ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the time paſt? anſwered: <hi>As the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Eſd. 4.</note> 
               <hi>raine is more than the droppes, and as the fire exceedeth the ſmoke, ſo the portion that is paſt hath the vpper hand.</hi> Whereas, in deede, there is no proofe of defalcation, for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that this Scripture is <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> and therefore no ſufficient proofe, and they erre with the Papiſts, affuming that it is Canonicall: and their argumentes which they borrow of Theodorus Bibliander, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Saint Ierom, a man of greater autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie than himſelfe, to proue that it is Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, becauſe it teacheth the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting kingdome of Chriſt, the reprobation of the Gentiles, and election of the Iewes, are not ſufficient proofs, becauſe the works
<pb facs="tcp:173988:10"/> of men do teach the ſame things, wheras no workes of men are Canonicall. Eſdras liued about 3600 years after the creation, ſo that then the time to come might bee ſhorter than the time paſt, without any defalcation of yeares or dayes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they diſpute in this maner: A thouſand yeares with God, are as one day. <note place="margin">Pſal. 90. 2. Pet.</note> But as God labored ſix dayes and reſted the ſeuenth: ſo ſhal God be in action (as it were) for the preſeruation of the ſame, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering togither of his Church ſixe thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares, proportionably to thoſe ſixe dayes, and then ſhall be a perpetuall Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both. And as in time paſt they began the celebration of the Sabboth, at the midſt of <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> the ſixt day, making halfe holy day, and ſo laboured the weeke daies but fiue daies and an halfe: ſo halfe of the laſt thouſand years muſt be cut off. It ſhall not be needfull to anſwer the preſumptions of men, which are not grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon ſcripture nor ſound rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but the weaknes of that argument ſhall appeare by the like, 1500. years before god, are not ſo much as one hour. For ſo writeth the Apoſtle: <hi>Babes, it is the laſt houre.</hi> Fifteen hundred years are expired, &amp; yet the houre <note place="margin">1. Iohn 2</note> is not ended, but 24. hours make one day, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:173988:10"/> that if 1500. years be reckoned but for one houre, ſixe and thirtie thouſand yeares are but one day before god, ſo that, if the world continue ſix dayes, it muſt indure, by that computation, two hundred and ſixteene thouſand yeares. This is as good a reaſon out of Saint John, to proue the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the worlde two hundred and ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen thouſand yeares, as that is out of S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to proue that it ſhall ſtand 6000. years.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, thus they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude: <hi>Chriſt was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1 Heb. 2</note> 
               <hi>in the fleſh in the laſt time.</hi> And, <hi>He was offered once in the end of the world.</hi> But, if the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were the end of the world, the middle was paſt, therefore but 2000. yeares were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind. If they take the middle for that which is <hi>intermedium,</hi> whatſoeuer is betweene the beginning and the ending, as commonly it is taken, then it was the middle immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the creation, and the middle ſhall continue vntill the laſt conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and, in that ſenſe the middle is not yet paſt: but if they take it ſtrictly, as in Geometrie it is defined: <hi>Medium eſt id quod aequè diſtat ab extremis,</hi> that which is of equal diſtance betweene the beginning and the ending: if the middle were but then paſt, when foure thouſand yeares were expired,
<pb facs="tcp:173988:11"/> it is a neceſſarie demonſtration, that there could bee no leſſe than foure thouſande yeares to come after Chriſtes paſsion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there muſt bee as great diſtance of time from the middle to the ende, as was from the beginning to the middle.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, all the ſignes and tokens, which go any diſtance of time before the day of iudgement, are alreadie come to paſſe, that now no ſigne can bee looked for, but onely thoſe which muſt be ſhewed immediatelie vpon his comming to iudgement. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the accompliſhment and fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of al theſe propheſies, cannot ſhew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs how neare it is to the ende, we denie that all theſe tokens and ſignes are come to paſſe, for there is yet one propheſie to bee fulfilled, which is the laſt and generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of the Iewes. That they muſt bee conuerted, Saint Paule proueth by eight reaſons. The firſt is from the end of their <note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> reiection, which is, not that they ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but ſeeing the conuerſion of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, be prouoked to emulation. The ſecond <hi>à minori,</hi> if their fall be riches to the world, how much more ſhall their reconciliation be life to the dead? The thirde from the condition of the Patriarch Abraham, if
<pb facs="tcp:173988:11"/> the firſt fruits be holy, ſo is the lumpe, if the roote, ſo are the branches. The fourth from Gods omnipotency which is able to receiue them againe. The fift <hi>à veriſimili,</hi> if God ingrafted the wilde oliue contrarie to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, howe much more ſhall the naturall branches be ingrafted into their naturall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue? The ſixt, from the authoritie of Eſay and Ieremie, which affirme the ſame. The ſeuenth, from a diſtinction, concerning the Goſpell, they are enemies for our ſake, but touching the election, beloued for their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſake. The eightreaſon is, <hi>ab analogia,</hi> as the Gentiles were firſt reiected for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe, yet afterward receiued, ſo, the time ſhall come when the reiected Iewes ſhall beleeue, and ſo be receyued againe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and all Iſraell ſhall bee ſaued.</p>
            <p>But, that they ſhall be turned or conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo generally, being in number ſo many, in places ſo diſperſed, in religion ſo backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, in one moment, or a ſhort time, I thinke no man of iudgement will ſuppoſe, much leſſe affirme.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Henoch and Elias were the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth from Adam, Henoch in generation, Elias in computation of liues. But there is a
<pb facs="tcp:173988:12"/> proportion betweene them and the ages of the world, for as the death of the body raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ouer theſe ſixe, Adam, Seth, Enos, Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, Mahaleel, Iared, but the ſeuenth which was Henoch, neuer died, but was tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and likewiſe in computation of liues, Adam liued vnto Methuſalem, Methuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem vnto Sem, Sem vnto Iacob, Iacob vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Amram, Amram vnto Ahia, Ahia vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Elias, which being the ſeuenth died not, but was taken vppe; ſo death muſt reigne ouer the world ſixe thouſand yeares, and then ſhall bee euerlaſting life. But, to this, and ſuch like, their preſumptions, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine coniectures, becauſe they vrge vs with the anſwere of the Angell <hi>vriel,</hi> I will refute them with the anſwere of the ſame Angel in the ſame place. <hi>Weigh me the weight of the fire meaſure the blaſt of the wind,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Eſd. 4</note> 
               <hi>or call againe the day that is past, but if no man borne can doe that, howe ſhall thy veſſell be able to comprehende the wayes of the moſt higheſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Papiſts, not directly, but by a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent, take vpon them to point at, not onely the yeare, but rather the day and houre of the laſt iudgement. For <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> in one of his demonſtrations, holdeth
<pb facs="tcp:173988:12"/> that Antichriſt after hee is reueled muſt reigne but three yeares and ſixe monethes, and then be deſtroyed fortie and fiue dayes before the comming of Chriſt, which, if it were true, Antichriſt beeing once reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, it were no cunning to define the day and houre of the appearance of our Sauiour Chriſt, which is a ſecrete, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to the Angels in heauen. This doctrine refuteth it ſelfe, therefore I let it paſſe, and come to the third poynt, which ſheweth howe farre wee may be bolde to determine of the propmquitie and neernes of the appearance of our Sauiour Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Angell <hi>Vriel</hi> ſayeth to Eſdras: <hi>If I ſhoulde aske thee howe deepe dwellinges</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Eſd. 4</note> 
               <hi>are in the middeſt of the Sea, or how great Springes are in the beginning of the depth, or the ſtretching out of the Heauen, or which are the borders of Paradiſe, peraduenture thou wouldeſt ſay to mee: I neuer went downe to the deepe, I neuer deſcended downe into Hell, nor clymed vppe into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: but nowe, I asked thee of fire and wind, and of the day whereby thou haſt paſſed, and from whence thou canst not bee ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and yet thou canſt giue me no aunſwere of them. Howe then ſhall thy veſſell bee able</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:173988:13"/> 
               <hi>to comprehend the wayes of the higheſt?</hi> Why ſhould fooliſh man, which is made of the <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> baſeſt mould enter into the ſecretes of his God, who <hi>is wiſe in heart, mightie in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob. 9.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrength, who remoueth the earth out of her place, cauſeth the pillars thereof to ſhake, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth the ſunne and it riſeth not, cloſeth vp the ſtarres as vnder a ſignet, createth Arcturus, Orion, and Pleiades, and the climates of the South, ſpreadeth out the heauens, walketh on the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob. 11.</note> 
               <hi>height of the Sea, whoſe perfection is higher than heauen, deeper than hell, longer than the earth, broder than the Sea.</hi> Our ſauiour Chriſt ſaith: <hi>Watch ye therefore, becauſe ye know not what houre your Maiſter will come:</hi> And to <note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> that ende may we not knowe, becauſe wee ſhould alwayes watch. We are taught by the Scriptures, that God hath two bookes, and both of them are written for vs to read, and in thoſe bookes are contained al things concerning this argument, which are either conuenient for vs to knowe, or lawfull for vs to ſearch. The one is the booke of grace, which is the volume of the olde and newe Teſtament, though euer lying open, yet ſealed vp to many wiſe, learned, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete men of the world, becauſe reading they vnderſtand not, for, they read as did
<pb facs="tcp:173988:13"/> the Eunuch the propheſie of Eſay, but it is very eaſie to be vnderſtoode of all belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, <note place="margin">Acts 8.</note> for whoſe ſaluation it was written by the holy Ghoſt, which is the finger of gods <note place="margin">Exod. 8.</note> hand. The other is the booke of nature, that great frame and engine of the worlde, alwayes lying open to the view of naturall men, and neuer ſhut vp, becauſe it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but <hi>epiſtola ſcripta ad humanum genus,</hi> a long letter or a large epiſtle writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, not to the faithfull onely, but to al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, to all which bee illuminated by the light of nature, not ſuch a letter as is ſealed vp with his priuie ſignet <hi>Multi vocati, pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 20 2. Tim. 2.</note> 
               <hi>electi,</hi> many are called and few are choſen, and <hi>ſolus deus nouit ſuos,</hi> only God knoweth his; but his letters patents, wherein is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Domini eſt terra &amp; plenitudo eius,</hi> the <note place="margin">Pſal. 24 Pſal. 8</note> earth is the Lordes and all that therein is, and <hi>Quid eſt homo quod memor es illius?</hi> what is man that thou art ſo mindefull of him? alwayes lying open that euery man may read, and written in <hi>folio,</hi> that ſtanding a far off they may reade, and in great capital letters, that running they may reade. And vpon more than we can finde written in theſe two bookes, wee may not preſume. But, as for the third booke which is called
<pb facs="tcp:173988:14"/> the booke of life, and the booke ſealed vp <note place="margin">Phil. 4 Dan. 12 Exod. 32 Apoc. 22 Apoc. 5</note> with ſeuen ſeales, which is the ſecrete will of God, it is not reuealed to Angels, much leſſe to men: in that booke are written gods ſecret counſels, concerning the election of Iacob, and reprobation of Eſau, the calling of the Gentiles, and reiecting of the Iewes, which go beyond the capacitie of man, and finallie of this laſt and dreadfull iudgement, the time whereof the Apoſtles deſired to knowe, but no directer aunſwere was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them than this: <hi>Of the day and houre</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24</note> 
               <hi>knoweth no man, &amp;c:</hi> And <hi>it is not for you to knowe the times and ſeaſons which the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 1</note> 
               <hi>Father hath appoynted in his owne power.</hi> Daniel deſired to knowe, but it was ſaide <note place="margin">Dan. 12</note> vnto him: <hi>But thou, O Daniel ſhut vp the wordes and ſeale vp the Booke till the ende of the time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe out of the booke of nature, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this time, though we cannot diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher vnto you the houre, day, moneth or yeare, becauſe it is not there reuealed, yet in that booke we do read that it is very neare. For, nature beginneth generally to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her woonted courſe, the mother Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the worlde, whereof things in this lower world are made, doe looſe their
<pb facs="tcp:173988:14"/> qualities and naturall vigour which they had before, the Starres and Planets of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen waxe dimme and olde, not ſo well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to preſerue our earthly bodies, the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall ſpheres bee almoſt wearie of their woonted motions and regular volubilitie, the prince of the lights of Heauen, which <note place="margin">Pſal. 19</note> before came as a bridegroome trimmed out of his chamber dooth not looke vppon vs with ſo chearefull an aſpect, and that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, which before did runne his vnwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried race, dooth as it were by a langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing faintneſſe beginne to ſtand and reſt himſelfe, the times and ſeaſons of the yeare doc blend themſelues with diſordered and confuſed mixture, the windes are in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to breath out their laſt gaſpe, our mother the earth defeated of that aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of heauenly influence which at the firſt ſhee had, is out of heart, waxeth bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and dead like the wombe of Sara: the herbes and ſimples which are appointed <note place="margin">Gen: 11 Rom. 4</note> for medicines for mans bodie, haue almoſt loſt their operation and vertue, and man himſelfe, whom all theſe things do ſerue, is of lower ſtature, leſſe ſtrength, ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter life than at the firſt he was, ſo that there is a generall decay of natures, and in euerie
<pb facs="tcp:173988:15"/> leafe of that booke it is written, that the frame of that heauenly arch erected ouer our heads muſt very ſhortly loſe &amp; diſſolue it ſelfe. In the other booke, which is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bible, are many propheſies concerning that laſt houre, and all the ſignes and tokens which in theſe propheſies are foretold to go any diſtance of time before the day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are already come to paſſe, onely one excepted, which is the laſt and generall vocation of the Iewes, which when, and in how ſhort ſpace it ſhalbe fulfilled, the Lord onely in his wiſdome knoweth. But among all thoſe tokens, this is principally to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which Chriſt foretold. <hi>As the dayes of Noah were, ſo ſhal the comming of the ſon of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be.</hi> In the daies of Noah I note two things, <note place="margin">Matt. 24 Gen. 6.</note> firſt, great oppreſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in that there were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants vpon the earth, ſecondly, a general cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of all fleſh, inſomuch that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented him that he had made man vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, and he was ſory in his heart. And by that propheſie it is plaine, that the ſonne of man now ſtandeth knocking at our doores, becauſe the like times to the daies of Noah are come againe. Touching the firſt, the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants are nowe more in number, prouder in heart, loftier in their lookes, ſtouter in their
<pb facs="tcp:173988:15"/> gate and pace, than they were in the dayes of Noah: for almoſt euery rich man is a gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant in the place where he dwelleth. The potters veſſell ſaid to the brazen caldron. <hi>Tua mihi vicinitas non placet ſoror:</hi> I will not come nigh thee for feare of a knocke, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dareth the poore man dwell by the rich for feare of a check. It is not ſafe for the poore man to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend with the rich though his cauſe be good, no more than it is for the earthen pitcher to iuſtle with the brazen cauldron ſwimming down the ſtreame, leſt it be broken all to potſherds. Better it is to loſe his right, with peace and quietnes. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port is made of an Emperor which deſired to marry his owne daughter, he asked coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the lawyers, whether the marriage were lawfull or not? they aunſwered, that they knew no law in particular which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth a father to marry his daughter, but neuertheleſſe they had found out a law in generall which would permit the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe euery mighty ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might do what him liſted. I wiſh that all men to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſword of iuſtice is committed, would remember the propheſie of the poet Chaucer.</p>
            <q>
               <l>When faith failes in in prieſts ſawes,</l>
               <l>And Lords hests are holden for lawes,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:173988:16"/>
               <l>And robberie is holden purchaſe,</l>
               <l>And lecherie is holden ſolace,</l>
               <l>Then ſhall the lond of Albion,</l>
               <l>Be brought to great confuſion.</l>
            </q>
            <p>We reade of Nimrod which was a great hunter vpon the earth. But I feare leaſt in <note place="margin">Gen. 10</note> our dayes, in ſtead of that one, we haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nimrods, which hunt as the Lion did with foxes and aſſes, which when they had taken their prey, the Lion beeing able by force to take all to himſelfe, woulde ſeeme verie iuſt, and take no more than by right was due vnto him, and to impart the reſt to his fellow hunters. Wherefore, becauſe it is a rule: <hi>Cuius eſt partitio, eius non eſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio:</hi> The ſame may not bee both a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uider and a chooſer, he cauſed the Aſſe to diuide the ſpoyle. The Aſſe like a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>animal,</hi> as an Aſſe would doe, diuided it verie iuſtly into three equall portions, the Lion miſliking the diuiſion, tore the Aſſe in peeces, then he bid the Fox mend the diuiſion; the Foxe allotted the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part to the Lion, and little or nothing to himſelfe: whereupon, the Fox was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to be the beſt geometrician. As for the ſecond, God may now repent him, as he did in the dayes of Noah, that hee made
<pb facs="tcp:173988:16"/> man vppon the earth, for the propheſie of Chriſt is fulfilled: <hi>Charitie waxeth colde,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 13 Mat. 24</note> 
               <hi>iniquitie doth abound: faith is not found vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth.</hi> There is a ripeneſſe of ſinne, <note place="margin">Apoc. 14</note> and what can bee expected but an harueſt, that the Angell thruſt his ſharpe ſickle on the earth and cutte downe the cluſters of the Vineyard, and caſt them into the great wine fatte of the wrath of God. Sinne is not now <hi>Peccatum habitans,</hi> but <hi>regnans,</hi> not making his abode with vs, but raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ouer vs, it hath gotten a longer and larger iuriſdiction ouer the world, than Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar had ouer the Senat, which obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Perpetuam Dictaturam:</hi> An euerlaſting Dictatorſhip, the like not heard of before. The ſinnes which now raigne are ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, that it may well be ſaid: <hi>Vir bonus eſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal rarum:</hi> He which will find a iuſt and vpright man vpon the earth, muſt take a candle at noone dayes, and ſeeke in the ruſhes as it were for a pinne or a needle that is loſt, and ſay with Diogenes: <hi>Quaero ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem,</hi> I ſeeke a man. And which is more, they be <hi>Clamantia peccata,</hi> Crying ſinnes, becauſe the crie of them aſcendeth vp into <note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> heauen, as did the bloud of Abell for vengeance againſt vs, and the ſoules of the
<pb facs="tcp:173988:17"/> martirs vnder the altar, vſury, ſimony, bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <note place="margin">Apoc. 6 Gen. 3 Pſal. 32</note> and contempt of the miniſters of God, &amp; pride which was the firſt cauſe of the fal of man. The prophet Dauid ſaid, <hi>beati quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iniquitates ſunt tectae, &amp;c:</hi> Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are couered, and to whom the Lord hath imputed no ſin, but now it is become a prouerbe among vs, <hi>Happy is that child whoſe father goeth to the deuill.</hi> The Iewes which were accounted the extremeſt vſurers in the world, tooke intereſt only of ſtrangers, and not of their owne nation, but our countrimen worſe than Iewes, ſpare none, and which is the greateſt hypocriſie, no man maketh more account outwardly of them which preach againſt vſury, than doth the vſurer, and thoſe which wil hear 3. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in a day, thinke thirty pounds intereſt in the hundred to be too little. And, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they ſeeme outwarly zealous, yet haue they within them, that I may vſe the ſpeach of the apoſtle, <hi>conſcientiam cauteria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,</hi> a conſcience feared with an hot iron, <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4</note> and, notwithſtanding their diligence in fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting ſermons, and reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, they forget what is written there, that it ſhall be harder for any rich man to enter into the kingdome of heauen, than it ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:173988:17"/> for a camell to paſſe through the eie of a <note place="margin">Luke 18</note> needle, but, that no vſurer ſhall dwell in the Lords tabernacle, nor reſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his holy hill. <note place="margin">Pſal. 15</note> William Rufus, once king of England, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for pride, which pride in reſpect of theſe dayes were great humilitie. His chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine brought him in the morning a newe pair of breeches, the beſt that could be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the price was foure ſhillings. The king ſwore no ſmall oath, that he would haue a paire which ſhould coſt him a marke in ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: no breeches were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo high a price, the chamberlaine to ſatisfie the kings mind, brought a worſe paire then the firſt, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that they coſt a marke. I mary, quoth Rufus, here are a pair of breeches for a king. Four ſhillings the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſufficed for a pair of bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for a king, but I feare ſhortly it will be a prouerbe: 500. pounds for a paire of pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taples for a ſubiect. Euery man can bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to goe in ſoft rayment, as they doe in <note place="margin">Luke 16</note> the courts of princes, &amp; to be clothed with purple, as was the rich glutton which is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in hell, euery man can take delight in the Babilonian garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which is framed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this world, but few will put on the wedding garment, which is <note place="margin">Mat. 12</note> charitie, and a good conſcience; men will be
<pb facs="tcp:173988:18"/> clothed like women, and women like men, not regarding the curſe denounced of the Lord. But as for the girdle of truth, the breſt <note place="margin">Deut. 22 Ephe. 6</note> plate of righteouſneſſe, the ſhield of faith, the helmet of ſaluation, the ſworde of the ſpirit, and the ſhooes of peace, they are layde aſide as olde ſhooes, and neuer come within our Wardrops. You will not bee clothed as the kings daughter which is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <note place="margin">Pſal. 41</note> within, but like painted ſepulchres which are faire without, and within are full of dead mens bones.</p>
            <p>Offices are commonly ſolde, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no maruaile though the officers be corrupt. Whoſoeuer can bee entertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſeruice of a noble man, is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation for his maiſters ſake, be he neuer ſo baſe; but the miniſters of Gods worde, which ſerue the king of kings and Lord of Lords, whoſe ſeruice is perfect freedome, in whoſe houſe it is better to bee a doore keeper, than to dwell in the tabernacles of princes, euen him whome all other kings and lords ought to ſerue, are deſpiſed for their ſeruice ſake, be they neuer ſo nobly diſcended. But I haue text for them: <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10 Iohn 10 Luke 13 Luke. 21</note> 
               <hi>heareth you, heareth me: and whoſoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me, and hee that deſpiſeth</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:173988:18"/> 
               <hi>me, diſpiſeth him that ſent me.</hi> Our Sauiour Chriſt tolde his Apoſtles that they ſhould be hated of all men for his ſake, and at that time it was no great marvaile, becauſe they liued among Iewes and infidels; but nowe we are in maner hated of chriſtians, &amp; moſt of al of them which make the greateſt ſhew of zeale, and profeſsion of religion, and are the greateſt frequenters of ſermons. They are as cruell as Pharao of Egypt which <note place="margin">Exod. 5</note> woulde compell the children of Iſrael in their bondage to make brickes and tyles, but denied them ſtraw and morter to work withall, ſo they call vpon vs for hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but detaine from vs our tithes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, which are as due to vs as their lands are to them, and without which it is as vnpoſsible to keepe hoſpiralitie, as it was for the Hebrues to woorke without ſtraw. I deny not, but in ſom ſort, the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the church are competent, but they are in the hands of lay me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to maintain their pride: we beare the name, and they reape the commodity, and yet ſlander vs, becauſe we keepe not hoſpitalitie. Wil. Rufus was wont to ſay, that the Church breade was ſweet bread, and Iulian the apoſtata would rob the miniſters pretending conſcience,
<pb facs="tcp:173988:19"/> becauſe ſo much liuing was a burden vnto them, &amp; an hinderance vnto their miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, we haue many as hungry as Wil. Rufus, and as conſcionable as Iulian the Apoſtata, vpon whom, though God doth not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew tokens of his wrath as he did vpon them, which cauſed one to be ſtroken with a dart vpon earth, and the other with an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row from heauen, yet, there is an heauie iudgement reſerued for them, &amp; their dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſleepeth not. I beſeech you pardon me though I refrain not to ſpeak, for I feare leaſt being ſilent, I ſhould be guilty of their ſins, and incur the reprehenſion of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Dauid: <hi>When thou ſaweſt a theefe, thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal: 50</note> 
               <hi>didſt run with him.</hi> Salomon though a king, not aſhamed to bee a preacher, ſheweth vs that all things haue a time. But one thing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially I note, where he ſaith: <hi>There is a time to gather ſtones, and a time to caſt ſtones a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 3</note> The time of gathering ſtones was a time of deuotion, and it continued in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land about 900. yeares, and now that time is ended, the time of caſting away ſtones is gaped after, to ſuppres that in one age which was, not erected in many: which time, in vaine do they looke for, as long as our moſt gracious lady and miſtreſſe, our dread ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine
<pb facs="tcp:173988:19"/> Queene Elizabeth reigneth, and moſt humbly I beſeech God, that if it be his moſt bleſſed will, ſhe may reigne ouer vs to the worlds end. But, when that time ſhall come, it will be manifeſt to all the world, that ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity hath got the vpper ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that nothing can then be expected, but fire and brimſton to raine from heauen as it did vpon Sodom, or elſe, it wil be high time for vs to crie: <hi>Etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19. Apoc. 22.</note> 
               <hi>veni Domine Ieſu, venicito, Come Lord Ieſus, come quickly.</hi> I know my ſharp reprehenſion doth offend them which be guiltie, but I conſider that I am ſent as a ſheepe to hunt after wolues, and I know the worſt that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening wolues can do; they can but deuour. I muſt do my maiſters meſſage, and if you <note place="margin">Matt. 10 Acts. 12. and 8</note> regard it not. I ſhake the duſt off my feet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and your blood bee vpon your owne heads, I am cleare, I feare not man which hath power ouer the bodie only, but God which is able to deſtroy both body and <note place="margin">Matt. 10</note> ſoule in hell fire. The crying ſin of ſimonie reigneth euery where, and patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces chuſe their miniſters, not as the gods choſe their trees into their patronage for good qualities: Iupiter the oke, becauſe it was good for building: Neptune the pine becauſe it ſerued to make ſhips: Apollo the
<pb facs="tcp:173988:20"/> bay, becauſe it was greene: Hercules the popple, becauſe it was ſtreight and tall like himſelf, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding all theſe trees were without fruit, becauſe the gods were hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably minded, and would not <hi>Fructu honore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vendere,</hi> ſell promotions for commoditie: but as the goddeſſe Minerua, which choſe the oliue tree, becauſe it was fat. At the firſt the patronage of benefices was committed to Gentlemen vpon truſt, becauſe great confidence was in them repoſed, but nowe they haue gotten it into their hands, they do as it was ſaid of pope Alexander:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>endit Alexander claues, altaria Christum.</l>
               <l>Emerat ille prius, vendere iure poteſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>They acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt the lords portion their own fee ſimple and inheritance, they bought the patronage, &amp; therfore they wil ſell the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, ſo that they which vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſpeciall truſt repoſed in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue other men were choſen patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; defenders, are become rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers &amp; ſpoilers of the church. They cry out for a learned miniſtery, wheras in deed they pick but quarels with vs, intending nothing les tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a learned miniſtery, for they wil wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly preſent none, but ſuch as are baſe, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; beggerly, becauſe ſuch perſons wil eaſily accept of benefices vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnlawful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Many painful ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts do earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb facs="tcp:173988:20"/> to enter into the lords harueſt, but they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be ſet a worke, for they know no way but one, to be ſet ouer a flocke, which is in right, the gift of the holy ghoſt, but by the ſorcery of St. Magus, whoſe art magick is ſo common throughout the land, that there be few patrons which are not bewitched with the ſame, they haue forgot the text: <hi>he that taketh counſell of a ſorcerer ſhall die the death.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Leui. 20</note> The voice of Iudas to the high prieſts, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſold Chriſt, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon in their mouthes, <note place="margin">Mat. 24</note> 
               <hi>quid mihi dabitis, &amp; ego trada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vobis?</hi> What wil you giue, &amp; I wil giue you the preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but they reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber not the anſwer of Si. Peter to Si. Magus, <hi>thy mony periſh with thee,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 8</note> 
               <hi>which thinkeſt, &amp;c.</hi> This corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wilbe the decay of al religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore it is now high time that Moſes aſsiſt his brother Aaron. But haue ye not hard the fable of the hors &amp; the aſſe, which were loded togither &amp; ready to go their iourny? the aſſe being ouerladen made his mone to the horſe that he would eaſe him, but was neied at by the horſe that caried the lighter burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the Aſſe tired &amp; died by the way: wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the husbandman laid the dead aſſes pack vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hors, ſo that wheras before he bore but I. burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he was conſtraind to cary 2, &amp; when his backe was broken, hee could but lament his miſerie.
<pb facs="tcp:173988:21"/> The horſe betokeneth the nobility, becauſe he is fit for warre, and is <hi>generoſum animal,</hi> a noble beaſt. The ſily aſſe becauſe he is ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, fit by nature to beare heauy burdens, beaten, kicked, &amp; ſpurned at by euery one, doth repreſent the cleargie, which are ſore loaded with ſlanders and manifeſt wrongs, being ſtrooken on the right cheeke turne <note place="margin">Mat. 5</note> the left, being robbed of their cote, giue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their cloke, being curſed, they bleſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiled, reuile not againe. I need not tell you the morall of this fable, for <hi>Verbum ſapienti dictum ſat eſt,</hi> A word ſpoken to a wiſe man will ſuffice.</p>
            <p>Ye haue heard how the ſonne of man ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth knocking at your doores, and that now it is not an houre to his comming to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and come he will ſuddenly when he is not looked for. What then? Shall the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <note place="margin">Mat. 25</note> virgins ſlumber in the darke while the bridegroom paſſeth by? Shal Sampſon ſnort in Dalilaes lap in the middeſt of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins? <note place="margin">Iud. 16 Mat. 3 Luke 12</note> Shall the diſciples ſuffer Chriſt to ſleep while the ſhip is couered with waues? ſhal the couetous man enlarge his barnes &amp; ſay to his ſoule take thy reſt for many years, whereas that night his ſoule ſhall be taken from him? ſhall Loth build ſtately towers
<pb facs="tcp:173988:21"/> in Sodom being warned by the Angell to depart thence with ſpeed, becauſe it ſhalbe deſtroyed with brimſtone from heauen? why then doe we purchaſe lands as if wee would dwell alone, and lay vp money as if we would liue alone vpon the earth? why do we erect ſuch loftie buildings, the ground<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worke whereof is laid of ſtrife and diſcord, the morter whereof is tempered with the tears of widowes, the windowes beautified with the ſpoile of Orphanes, the beams and ſupporters, of the fal of good yeome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Why do we ſay (with the Idumea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) of gods houſe, <hi>Downe with it, downe with it, to the ground.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 137</note> 
               <hi>Raſe it vp, raſe it vp to the pauement,</hi> and raiſe our own houſes as high as the wals of Troy, or rather, if it might be, as the tower of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel? ſeeing that we cannnt inioy them lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than an houre. Galen maketh mention of a melancholy man, which reading in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, how Atlas ſupported heauen with his ſhoulders, receiued ſo deepe an impreſsion of the ſame in his mind, that he was in a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily feare leaſt Atlas ſhould faint, and let heauen fall vpon our heads. And, ſhall we which be Chriſtians liue in ſuch carnall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, that when we ſee, as it were with our eies, and heare dayly with our eares, that
<pb facs="tcp:173988:22"/> heauen cracketh, haue ſo little feeling as to think heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would ſtand for euer? let vs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Noah enter into the arke, let vs with Lot depart ſpeedily out of Sodom, &amp; that as Lot himſelf did, which we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t forward, not as his wife which looked backe, and was turned into a pillar of ſalt, let vs with Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias prepare our ſelues to die, and bid the world adue. Let vs as Chriſt willeth vs gird vp our loines, haue our lamps lighted in our hands, that we may be ready to meete the bride. Let vs rather folow the example of ſir <hi>Tho. More,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a petition by a woman, as hee went to his execution, aunſwered: Woman, I am now going about the kings buſines, I haue no leyſure to read petitions; than of Richard the third in Boſworth field, who being him ſelfe as a deadman, prepared to execute the L. Standlies ſon, his friends told him, it was not then any time to do execution, but high time to looke to himſelfe. I wiſh that the great Polititians and Wizards of this world, who intend as much ſacriledge as he did murther, would begin to be as wiſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, as they are towards the world, and at the laſt conſider, that it is nowe no time to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit ſacriledge, but it is high time
<pb facs="tcp:173988:22"/> for them to think on their owne ſaluation. S. Peter putteth them in mind of two god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditations far more fit for theſe times, and moſt profitable for the health of their ſoules, Frſt, ſaith he, <hi>Seeing all thoſe things</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3</note> 
               <hi>muſt be diſſolued, what maner of perſons ought you to be in holy conuerſation and godlines, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for, &amp; haſtning to the comming of the day of God, by the which the heauens being on fire muſt be diſſolued, and the elements ſhall melt with heat?</hi> Secondly, <hi>we muſt looke for a new heauen and a newe earth, according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, wherein righteouſnes doth dwel: land ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that wee looke for ſuch things, wee muſt bee diligent, that we may bee found without ſpot or blameleſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some what remaineth to be ſpoken of the ſecond part, which is, of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming the Apoſtle taketh for a moſt ſure ground to prooue that it is the end of the world, where hee ſaith: <hi>Yee haue heard that Antichriſt ſhal come: euen now there are many Antichriſts, whereby wee knowe that it is the last houre.</hi> In my diſcourſe of the comming of Antichriſt, firſt, becauſe that name hath many ſignifications, I will by foure diſtinctions take away the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie of the word. Secondly, I will define
<pb facs="tcp:173988:23"/> what Antichriſt is. Thirdly, I will deſcend to particulers, to diſcouer vnto you that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne, and to point out who is that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt whom the Apoſtle meaneth in this place, which ſhalbe a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proof againſt our countrime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Rhemes, that his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming is not now to be expected, but that he was 900. yeares ſince reueled to vs. Such as haue learned the rudiments of Grammer, are not ignorant, that this propoſition <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe things: likeneſſe and equalitie, in which ſenſe no man can be Antichriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man can be like him, or equal with him: any one which is in the place &amp; ſteed of another, according to which ſignification the pope falſly taketh vpon him that he is Antichriſt, which is, Chriſts deputie, or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car generall ouer his Church: contrarietie, and ſo euery one is Antichriſt, which is an aduerſarie vnto Chriſt, &amp; of this Antichriſt only the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, which maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth doctrine contrary to that which our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt hath taught, and therfore is an aduerſarie vnto him. And this Antichriſt which is Chriſts aduerſary, is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes in the ſcriptures, as Saint Iohn hath diſtinguiſhed in this place, either ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally for any aduerſary of the truth, or
<pb facs="tcp:173988:23"/> more eſpecially for ſuch an enemy as is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital, &amp; notorious aboue the reſt. For, where he ſaith, <hi>Euen now there are many Antichriſts,</hi> he ſpeaketh not of any one perſon, or ſtate, or ſucceſsion, or kingdome, aboue the reſt, but generally of all, which oppoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt any point of Chriſts doctrine. But, where he ſaith: <hi>Ye haue heard that Antichriſt ſhal come,</hi> he ſpeaketh <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of one which is eminent, and notoriouſly oppoſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, not in one point, but in the chief que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of Chriſtian religion.</p>
            <p>Againe, this famous and notorious Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, is either political, or eccleſiaſtical, for <note place="margin">Apoc. 13 1 Iohn. 4. Apoc. 13 Apoc. 17</note> the old empire of Rome vnder the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which Iohn calleth a beaſt with ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heads and ten hornes, is the politicall Antichriſt, which flouriſhed in the Apoſtles time, of which he ſaid: <hi>he is now alreadie in the world,</hi> but the eccleſiaſticall Antichriſt, which is called by 3. names, as the beaſt aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding out of the earth with 2. horns, &amp;, the harlot ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon the firſt beaſt, and the beaſt that was, &amp; is not, is the eight, &amp; is one of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which 3. names ſignifie one thing, that is, the ſtate of Popes raigning in the place of the Emperors (for, that is to ſit vpon the beaſt with ſeuen heads) and they are called a
<pb facs="tcp:173988:24"/> beaſt for their crueltie, a woman for their <note place="margin">Ezec: 23 Hoſea. 2 2. Theſ. 2</note> pride, an harlot for their idolatrie, which is ſpirituall fornication. And this Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Antichriſt is taken alſo two manner of waies by S. Paule, either properly, or figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiuely, properly for an whole bodie, or kingdome, or ſtate, which is oppoſite to Chriſt, where he ſaith: <hi>There muſt come a departure or a reuoltment firſt, and, the miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of iniquitie doth alreadie worke.</hi> In which words he ſpeaketh of a generall Apoſtacie from ſound religion. For, in Diuinitie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the rules of Logick, indefinite pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in matter contingent, are almoſt vniuerſall, not to bee vnderſtoode of ſome few, but either of all, or elſe of the greateſt part, as for example: <hi>Iniquitie ſhall abound,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 18 Matt. 24</note> 
               <hi>charitie ſhall waxe cold faith ſhal not be found vpon the earth:</hi> not the iniquitie, or faith, or charity of a few, is to be vnderſtood, but almoſt of all the inhabitants of the earth. Againe, <hi>with the whore haue committed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 17</note> 
               <hi>the inhabitants of the earth,</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is indefinite, yet generally to bee vnderſtoode, for ſo it is interpreted in the Chapter following: <hi>All nations haue drunk</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Apo. 18</note> 
               <hi>of the wine of the wrath of her fornication.</hi> But, where he ſaith: <hi>An aduerſarie that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth
<pb facs="tcp:173988:24"/> himſelfe aboue all that is called God, and ſitteth as god in the temple of god,</hi> by the figure <hi>Synechdoche,</hi> he meaneth only the head and prince of that Apoſtacie and reuoltment from Chriſt: Wherfore, Antichriſt is to be vnderſtoode in this place, in the firſt diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, according to the third ſignification, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for him that is oppoſed againſt Chriſt, and an aduerſarie vnto his truth, not euerie aduerſarie, but one more ſingular and noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious than the reſt, not politicall, but Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, not in the proper ſignification, for the whole bodie or kingdome, but by a <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nechdoche,</hi> for the head &amp; prince of that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Apoſtacie and rebellion.</p>
            <p>Hauing by diſtinctions vnfolded vnto you the ambiguitie of this name Antichriſt, and ſhewed howe it is to be vnderſtood in this place, I define him in this maner: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt is a ſucceſsion of Biſhops, diſciphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out by certaine notes and marks in the holy Scriptures, which profeſsing the name of Chriſt, doe oppoſe themſelues agaynſt him in many chiefe points of Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. That he is not one particular man but an whole ſucceſsion of many men, I prooue by theſe two reaſons: firſt, it was prophecied that Antichriſt that purple
<pb facs="tcp:173988:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> harlot, ſhould make drunke with the wine <note place="margin">Apo. 18</note> of her formicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, al the nations of the earth. And that Antichriſt, that two horned beaſt. ſhould giue life to the Image of the beaſt <note place="margin">Apoc. 13</note> which was deſtroied, that is, he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the decaied ſtate of the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, by ſetting vp new Emperours in the Weſt, which in reſpect of the former Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors are but Images, and very ſhadowes: that he ſhould make many peoples &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſubiect vnto himſelf. But theſe things could not bee brought to paſſe in one mans age, therefore Antichriſt is not one man, but a ſucceſsion of many. Secondly, no one Methuſalem could liue from the Apoſtles time vnto the end of the world, but Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is deſcribed in the Scriptures to bee ſuch a one as muſt liue from the Apoſtles time vntill the end of the world, as it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by S. Paul. For, of his beginning, hee ſaith, <hi>The miſterie of iniquitie doth alreadie worke,</hi> ſo that albeit he was not then reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <note place="margin">Theſ. 2. 2</note> becauſe that ſame <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that obſtacle or hinderance, which was the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, was not then remoued from Rome to Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinople, that he might giue place to the Pope, the time was not accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed when the head of iniquitie ſhould be
<pb facs="tcp:173988:25"/> ioined to the body, and ſo made perfect: yet S. Paul doth acknowledge that he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie come, when he himſelfe liued: and, of his ende, he faith: <hi>Hee muſt be conſumed with the breath of Gods mouth, and aboliſhed with the brightnes of his comming.</hi> But, the breath of Gods mouth is his word, and the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Sibilla the propheteſſe, foretold that he ſhould be deſtroyed with linnen, and paper (you knowe) is made of rags of linnen, and the Goſpell is written in paper, and this Goſpel weakeneth his kingdome, but he is not to be vtterly aboliſhed, but by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt. Therefore he is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not one man, but an whole ſucceſsion. The Papiſts of Rhemes argue againſt vs out of this very text, where he ſaith <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that Antichriſt, to proue that he is but one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular man, and not a ſucceſsion, as though this article: ſhould neceſſarily point at one, and demonſtrate ſome certaine man. But I will ſhew by two inſtances, how their argument doth not follow. Firſt, this article: doth not alwayes demonſtrate, for it is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed three maner of wayes in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, either <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratiuely to point at one particular, or
<pb facs="tcp:173988:26"/> emphatically, as in this place, or idlely, and to no purpoſe, as it is often and in euery page of the Greeke text. Let one example among a thouſande ſuffice, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <note place="margin">2. Iohn. 3</note> He that ſinneth is of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell not any one in particular, but euery one in a generalitie that ſinneth. Secondly if it were granted, (as it is denied) that this arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle doth neceſſarily import ſome one ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al man, according to the Grammatical ſenſe, yet doth it not follow, that one man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were to be vnderſtood, becauſe it is the maner of the ſcriptures to ſpeake of whole ſucceſsions as if it were but of one. Daniel <note place="margin">Dan. 7</note> deſcribeth three Monarchies, euery one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining diuerſe ſucceſsions of kings, by the names of three beaſts, the Empire of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians by one Lion, of the Perſians by one Beare, of the Macedonians by one Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard, he ſpeaketh of many as if he ſpake but of one: wherefore, although his maner of ſpeaking importeth but one, not one, but many are to be vnderſtood.</p>
            <p>That Antichriſt is a ſucceſsion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, not of Turkes or Pagans, or ſecular princes, it is plaine out of the text, <hi>he must</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſit in the Temple of God,</hi> not in the materiall temple of Salomon, which is now no more
<pb facs="tcp:173988:26"/> a temple, but the ſpirituall temple which is the Church, as S. Auguſtine doth inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret <note place="margin">De ciuit: Dei. li. 20 cap. 19</note> it: and he muſt aſſume vnto himſelfe Eccleſiaſticall authoritie, to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, to teach the worde, to ordaine Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which no ſucceſsion of ſecular princes euer did. The markes and tokens whereby Antichriſt is diſcloſed, are to be diſcuſſed in the particularizing and diſcouering vnto you who is Antichriſt that ſon of perdition, of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Littleton,</hi> a common lawier, in an Epilogue annexed to his booke, diſableth himſelfe, and detracteth from his owne learning, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he cannot warrant all to bee lawe which he hath written. Howſoeuer I haue not attayned vnto that meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Gods booke which hee had in the lawes of this land, yet I am more confident and I dare warrant you againſt all papiſts in the world, my ſoule for yours, that albeit ſome learned proteſtants being ouer-much modeſt, make a doubt whether Antichriſt be yet reuealed or not, affirming that if he be reuealed, he is the Biſhop of Rome: this doctrine which I ſhall deliuer you, is ſound and currant diuinitie, that the ſucceſsion of the Biſhops of Rome, which hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued
<pb facs="tcp:173988:27"/> about nine hundred yeeres, is that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt which is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For confirmation of this concluſion, I will alledge no other proofes than the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Scriptures, which do ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſet down all the miſteries of his reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. As for the Fathers, though far lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedder than any which liue in our dayes, their iudgements are different one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that no certaintie can bee gathered out of their writings, neither could they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to anie certaine knowledge heereof, for as much as Antichriſt which hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie diſcloſed himſelfe to vs, was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed when they liued, and it was vnpoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to know him but by the eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of things which now are, but then were not come to paſſe. Wherefore I admit no interpretation of ſcriptures concerning this propheſie, but onely the euent which is the moſt faithful interpreter of all propheſies. For, I am ſure there cannot be a more euident demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than this: wee ſee it alreadie come to paſſe, that all the prophecies concerning the reuelation of Antichriſt, are fulfilled in the Biſhops of Rome, and can al be verified of none elſe, therfore the Biſhops of Rome are Antichriſt. My antecedent I prooue in
<pb facs="tcp:173988:27"/> this manner: All the prophecies wherein he is deſcribed, are contained in the 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. and the Reuelation of S. Iohn. As for Daniel, though ſom of the learned haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorically applied his prophecies vnto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, which are properly ment of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochus, I deny that he euer writ of antichriſt at all. As for S. Paul, he propheſieth in this maner: <hi>That day ſhall not come, vnles there be a departure firſt, &amp; that man of ſin be diſcloſed, euen the ſon of perdition, which is an aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; exalteth himſelf againſt all that is called God, or that is worſhipped, ſo that he doth ſit as God in the temple of God ſhewing himſelf that he is God, &amp; now ye know what with-holdeth that bee might be reuealed in his time, for the miſtery of iniquity doth already work, only that which with-holdeth ſhal hinder ſtill, vntil it be taken away, and then ſhall the wicked one be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, whom the Lord ſhall deſtroy with the breath of his mouth, &amp; aboliſh with the bright<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of his comming, euan him, whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming is by the work of a Sathan, with al power &amp; ſignes, &amp; lying wonders.</hi> In which words, I obſerue 4. things which diſcloſe antichriſt vnto vs; his pride, <hi>He exalteth himſelfe aboue God,</hi> a <note place="margin">Esay 14</note> Lucifer did; his ſeat; <hi>He ſitteth in the temple of God, as if he were God,</hi> the time when he
<pb facs="tcp:173988:28"/> ſhuld begin to reigne, <hi>when that which with holdeth ſhould be taken away,</hi> which was the politicall Antichriſt, the Roman Emperors ſhould depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome: the maner how he ſhould eſtabliſh his kingdome, <hi>by ſignes and deluſions of Satan, &amp; lying wonders.</hi> But that the Biſhops of Rome take vpon them to be gods, and which is more, take to themſelues authoritie aboue God, it appeareth by the Laterane Counſell holden vnder Leo the tenth. wherein thus we reade: <hi>In Papaeſt omnis poteſtas ſupra ownes poteſtates tam caeli quam terrae,</hi> the popes power is aboue all powers both in heauen and earth. That he ſitteth in the Temple of God, it cannot be denied, becauſe his ſeat is Rome. The Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts can not prooue vnto vs that the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall temple of Salomon is heere to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, for that temple is deſtroyed, and that temple with the vſe wherevnto it was ordained, is vtterly aboliſhed by the lawe of God, ſo that if it were reedified, it were no more the temple of God, but a place of idolatry &amp; abomination, and if any ſuſpect that that temple may be builded againe, let him call to remembrance how the Iewes once obtained leaue of Iulian the Apoſtata to reedifie it, but God ſhewed manifeſt
<pb facs="tcp:173988:28"/> ſignes of his diſpleaſure, which cauſed the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation therof to be ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſunder with <note place="margin">Ruff. li. 10 38. &amp; 39.</note> earthquakes, and that which was builded in the day, to bee burnt vp with lighthing from heauen by night, Wherefore the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which is the ſeate of Antichriſt is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to be vnderſtood, as alſo, by reaſon of the wordes which goe before, where hee ſpeaketh of an Apoſtacie and reuoltment from true religion, which could not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iewes, among whome true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion then was not, and now is not profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſo that Antichriſt ſitteth in the church, and indeede hee hath choſen that Church for his ſeate, which was then moſt famous for the profeſsion of the Goſpell, as S. Paul himſelfe gaue teſtimony, when hee writ to the Romans, that their faith was heard of <note place="margin">Rom. 1</note> through the whole worlde. And, which is more than that, he ſitteth in the Church of God, as if he were God, intituling himſelfe Chriſts vicar general ouer the earth, which belongeth only to the holy Ghoſt which is God, whome Chriſt did ſubſtitute in his roome at his departure from vs, that hee might continue with vs, during the time of his abſence, ſaying: <hi>The Comforter which is the holy Ghoſt, the father will ſend in my name,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 14</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:173988:29"/> 
               <hi>he ſhall teach you al trueth: the Father ſhall giue you a Comforter which ſhal abide with you for euer.</hi> As for the time of his reuelation, hee was then to be reuealed, when the hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was taken away, which hinderance was the abode of the Emperours at Rome, which the Apoſtle ſpared to expreſſe in writing for theſe two reaſons: firſt, becauſe he made it ſufficiently knowen by word of mouth vnto the faithful: ſecondly, becauſe it might haue bin dangerous to the church, for the Emperours taking offence there at, would haue perſecuted the Chriſtians as buſi-bodies in matters of ſtate. But the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance was the Romane Emperors, which were firſt to depart from Rome, and giue place to the Popes, becauſe both Emperors and Popes could not reigne togither in one city. And that hinderance was taken away long ſince, when Conſtantine the great, tranſlated his imperiall ſeate to Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, and indowed the Popes with the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Rome, and a great part of Italy lying about it. The emperours then being farre off, and by reaſon of continuall warres with Saracens and enimies in the Eaſt, not able to maintaine their own right in the Weſt, the Popes incroched vpon them too farre, and
<pb facs="tcp:173988:29"/> vſurped ſo much authoritie, that they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded them cleane in Italy, and at their pleaſure ſet vp other Emperours in the Weaſt, but ſuch as would take an oathe to be ſubiect to the Apoſtolike See of Rome, and acknowledge the Popes to be vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Biſhops. So the hinderance was taken away when Conſtantine remoued to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, and Antichriſt was manifeſtly diſcloſed not long after, when <hi>Boniface</hi> the third obtained the title of vniuerſal Biſhop, which was 900. yeares agoe, for as Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <note place="margin">Lib. 4. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 38.</note> ſaith: none but Antichriſt would aſſume vnto him ſuch a title. As for the power of ſathan, and ſignes, and wonders, whereby his kingdome was eſtabliſhed, and the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people deceiued. I referre you vnto their owne legends of lies. Al the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of ſaint Iohn, concerning the diſcloſing of Antichriſt, are comprehended in the 13. and 17. chapters of his Reuelation. In his 13. chapter he deſcribeth two Antichriſts, the one Politicall, which flouriſhed in his time, the other Eccleſiaſticall, which was not then diſcloſed, but now reigneth, and beganne his dominion when the politicall Antichriſt was taken away. The politicall Antichriſt he deſcribeth in this maner: By
<pb facs="tcp:173988:30"/> the figure <hi>Senecdoche,</hi> taking Rome which was <hi>caput imperij,</hi> the chiefe Citie for the whole Empire. He calleth it a beaſt, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the example of Daniel, which called 4. <note place="margin">Dan. 7.</note> Monarchies foure beaſts.</p>
            <p>This beaſt hath the ſhape of a Beare, a Leopard, and a Lion, becauſe it conſiſted of three other Empires, of the Perſians Macedonians, and Babilonians before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, which by theſe three beaſts were repreſented. This beaſt had ten hornes, and ſeuen heads: the ten hornes are interpreted in the ſeuenteenth chapter to be ten kings or kingdomes, into which the old Empire was to bee diuided after the decay thereof, which afterward came to paſſe: the number of ten, which is certaine, beeing vſed for an vncertaine number, according to the maner of the Scriptures. The ſeuen heads, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeuenteene, are interpreted to be ſeuen hils, and ſeuen kings or orders of ſupreme Gouernours. But Rome hath ſeuen heades, whether you take them for hils or Kings, The hils which it was builded vppon, are theſe, Capitolinus, Palatinus, Auentinus, Celius, Exquilinus, Viminalis, Quirinalis. The orders of Gouernours by whom it was ruled at ſeuerall times by reaſon of alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb facs="tcp:173988:30"/> were Kings, Conſuls, Dictators, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemuiri, Triumuiri, Emperours of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Nobilitie of Rome, and laſtly, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of ſtrange families. Vpon thoſe heads, whether yee talke them for hils or Kings, were the names of blaſphemie: for, vpon the hils were builded Temples, dedicated to Minerua, Saturne, and heathen gods, and the Gouernors or Kings themſelues, were heathens, and worſhipped Idols of the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>One of the ſeuen heads, which was the race of the Emperours of the auncient Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nobilitie, was wounded in the perſon of Nero: which beeing the laſt of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Iulius, flue himſelfe; after whoſe death, the whole eſtate of the Empire was in ieopardy, by reaſon of diſention among them that did affect the Empire. But that deadly wound was healed againe by Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſran, which appeaſed all ſtrife, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſuſtained the burden of the Empyre: <hi>Fiue of thoſe kings,</hi> ſaith the Angel, <hi>are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, one is, the other is yet to come, and when he commeth, he muſt continue but a ſhort ſpace.</hi> Thoſe fiue which were fallen, were Kings, Conſuls, Dictators, Triumuiri, Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiri: which order of Gouernours were
<pb facs="tcp:173988:31"/> abrogated before S. Iohns time: the ſixt, which was of the Emperours of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Nobilitie of Rome, was then remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when S. Iohn liued, Domitian being Emperour; the ſeuenth, which was of the Emperors of ſtraunge families, was then to come: and when it came, it continued not long after the departure of Conſtantine into the Eaſt. To which hee addeth, <hi>The beaſt which was and is not, is the eight, and is one of the ſeuen, and ſhall go into deſtruction.</hi> By which eight, hee meaneth the order of the Popes. Of the beaſt, meaning the whole Empire, hee ſpeaketh in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>The beaſt which thou ſaweſt, was and is not, and ſhall aſcend out of the bottomleſſe pit:</hi> meaning that the Empire was, &amp; it was not. In the time of Domitian, it was, becauſe it ſtood, &amp; it was in the power of the Roman Nobility, but it was not in the ſame ſtate in which it was before, becauſe, from Iulius to Nero, it was hereditary, and tied vnto one familie, but Nero the laſt of that family be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, it was deuolued to Emperours of an other ſtocke and kindred: and it was to aſcend out of the bottomles pit, not in the former ſtate vnder the Emperours, but in another ſtate, vnder the Popes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173988:31"/>
            <p>Laſtly, he ſheweth the deſtruction of the political Antichriſt, ſaying: <hi>If any leade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way captiue, he muſt be led into captiuitie, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kill, he must be killed.</hi> Wherefore, nowe that hinderance is taken away which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of 2. Theſſ. 2. the Emperors giue place to the popes, and the Eccleſiaſticall Antichriſt is deſcribed in this maner: <hi>I ſaw another beaſt with two hornes aſcend out of the earth, &amp;c.</hi> This beaſt with two hornes, is all one with the purple harlot, Apocal. 17. for both be token the ſtate of the popedome, the eccleſiaſticall Antichriſt. This beaſt aſcendeth out of the earth, that is, it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of baſe parentage, hath two horns like like the lambe, for Antichriſt taketh vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to be Chriſtes vicar: ſpeaketh like the dragon, for he teacheth lies which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the old dragon the deuill, which was a liar from the beginning: giues life to the image of the firſt beaſt: for, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ancient emperours are decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the popes haue ordained new emperors in the weſt, which keep the ſame name and title, although being compared with them, they be but images or rather ſhadows. And the number of the name of this Antichriſt is 666. which number, both in Greeke and
<pb facs="tcp:173988:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> Hebrew, doth agree with the biſhops of Rome. In the Hebrew name <hi>Romijth,</hi> is the ſame number, for <hi>Reſh</hi> ſignifieth 200 <hi>Vau, 6 Mem,</hi> 40. double <hi>Iod, 20. Tau,</hi> 400, which being put together, make the number of the beaſt 666. Likewiſe, the Latine name <hi>Romanus</hi> written in Hebrue characters, maketh the ſame numbers, for <hi>Reſh</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth 200. as it did before, <hi>Mem, 40. Gnaiin 70. Nun 50. Vau 6. Schin</hi> 300, which make 666. Likewiſe, in Greeke, this name <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (which alſo is the name of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome) by adding to, according to the maner of the Greeks, in ſuch names as are made Greeke, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <hi>Caſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <hi>Nepthalim,</hi> ſignifieth 30. α 1. τ 300. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 10. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 50. ο 70. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 200 which make 666. Laſtly, concerning the place where this Eccleſiaſticall Antichriſt doth reign, that ſame beaſt with two horns, Which is called the whore, Apo. 17 (which whore in the ſame place, is interpreted to be a great Citie, which reigneth ouer the Kings of the earth) ſitteth vpon the beaſt with ſeuen heads and ten hornes, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth the Empire of Rome vnder the old Emperors: wherein it is manifeſt, that the Eccleſiaſtical Antichriſt, ſucceedeth the
<pb facs="tcp:173988:32"/> politicall, and ſitteth in the place of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperors: ſo that Antichriſt further than Rome is not to be ſought for.</p>
            <p>Thus haue you heard, how all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies concerning the diſcloſing of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt are fulfilled in the Biſhops of Rome, and, that all thoſe propheſies can not bee verified of any elſe, it is moſt euident for as much as no other Biſhops or ſecular Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces take vpon them to bee Chriſts Vicars generall ouer all the world: which is, to ſit as God in the Temple of God. No other States aſcribe vnto themſelues power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all powers in heauen and earth, which is, to exalt themſelues aboue God. No other States haue ſet vp Emperours in the Weſt, which is, to giue life to the image of the beaſt. Finally, no States beare ſway in a Citie builded vpon ſeuen hils, which Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie reigneth ouer the Kings of the earth, but they. Therefore I may ſafely make this concluſion: The ſucceſsion of the Biſhops of Rome, which hath beene ſince Boniface the third, and continued theſe nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, is that Antichriſt which Saint Iohn ſpeaketh of in this place. Wherefore, ſeeing the comming of Antichriſt, is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the latter end of the world, and
<pb facs="tcp:173988:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> this great and notorious Antichriſt hath beene reuealed vnto vs ſo long agoe: what remaineth, but that nowe wee lift vp our heads, for our Redemption draweth neere? and that we looke for a newe Heauen, and a new Earth, and the holy citie newe Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, comming downe from God out of Heauen, prepared as a beide trimmed for her husband? Againſt which comming, God grant we may be readie, our nakednes being clothed with wedding garments, our loynes girded, our ſteps lightned with our Lamps in our hands, for the Lambe Chriſt Ieſus his ſake, to whom with the father and the holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all honour, power, and glorie, both now and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
